Bet somebody that they've used Apache software within the last hour.
我敢打赌，刚才肯定有人在使用 Apache 软件
And they have, they have. Because not only are particular projects
结果也确实如此，不仅仅是因为特定的项目
particularly widespread, but the spread of projects is enormous.
特别受欢迎，还因为 Apache 项目影响深远
And so for instance, if they've used a credit card,
举例来说，如果使用信用卡，
if they've used television, if they've used a web browser, they've used a laptop.
看电视，浏览网页，用电脑
It's almost certain that they've used some Apache software,
这些都会和 Apache 软件有关
not knowing it, not necessarily seeing it.
只是你没意识到而已。
But it's almost certainly there.
但它们（Apache软件）一定是在那里的。
And it's unless you've been asleep for the last eight hours,
除非过去的几个小时，你一直在睡觉
it's really, really hard to go in a modern technological sense,
只要你和现代科技打交道
more than just a short period of time without using some Apache software.
哪怕只是很短的时间，你都会用到 Apache 软件。
Why do we give it away? Because it is what we do.
我们为什么将它们“拱手送人”？因为这就是我们要做的。
because the impact of open source is that openness.
因为开源本身的影响力就在于开放。
the ability for anyone to come and use and consume and contribute.
Apache 就是要让大家都来使用、消费并贡献
Hundreds and hundreds of years where knowledge was used to generate money.
过去几千年，知识一直用来赚钱
And the only success factor in society is how much money is my company making.
社会衡量成功的唯一标准就是你的公司赚了多少钱
I think the ASF has proven that even without making money,
而 Apache 软件基金会向人们证明，即使不赚钱
we did have a humongous impact in the way which the world runs.
我们也会给社会的运转带来巨大的影响
What would have defined success?
什么是成功？
The project success is based on the people rather than the code.
项目的成功在于人，而不是代码
And that's pretty much what comes about by the Apache way,
这就是 Apache 之道
The community is far more important than the code.
社区远比代码重要。
The code will survive whether or not the community does.
无论社区能否存活，代码都可以留存下来。
But it won't get any better or be enriched.
但它一定不会变得更好或更丰富。
They won't go on to succeed unless there's a community that support it.
除非有一个社区在背后支持它（们），否则它们不会持续发展下去
One of the things we're seeing nowadays
如今，
is that the lessons learned inside of IT，as far as how to create successful open source projects.
IT 界成功创造了一个又一个的开源项目，
But most important, how to create successful open source communities,
更重要的是，打造了一个又一个的开源社区，这些大家有目共睹
of which the apache way is most probably the best example of that
在这点Apache之道或许是最成功的案例
is starting to make inroads in other areas.
正开始在其他领域取得进展
This excessive open source is gonna expand beyond IT
这种拓展性的开源将逐渐扩张至IT界之外
is gonna expand beyond other software development in ecosystem.
将扩张并超越生态中其他软件的发展。
We're seeing open source cities now where the ideas of how to engage the populace,
我们可以看到开源的城市，在那里关于如何使全体居民参与
how to engage the citizens are using some of the tenets
如何使全体市民参与的想法正是借鉴了一些（开源的）信条
and some of the ideals of the apache way
以及一些Apache之道的理念
making sure that there is transparency in all the decision making processes of government.
确保政府的所有决策过程都可以做到透明。
I mean, this is how you build software,
这就是软件的开发模式
is by making sure that everyone involve, both the people who are creating the software,
让大家都参与其中，无论是软件工程师、
who are creating the software, creating the laws,
软件工程师、立法者
as well as the end users of the software and the citizens who were going to be abiding by the law.
还是终端的软件用户和那些遵从法律的市民们。
Is everything open? Everything is being done, in an open, public, and transparent manner.
是所有事情都是公开的吗？所有事情都是在一种公共的、开放的、透明的方式下完成的。
So we're seeing a lot of the tenets of successful open source,
所以我们看到很多成功开源软件的信条。
A lot of the means of the Apache way transcend the IT community,
Apache 之道的很多方法已经超越了 IT 社区，
and make inroads into government, corporate entities, a heavy industry, manufacturing, machining.
并运用在政府、公司企业、重工业、工厂、机械领域中。
And I think that's an incredible heritage for the movement we've created.
这笔遗产价值连城
At the use cases that get me excited are the ones that are about trying to address
让我感到最激动实际案例，是哪些想要试图解决
any one of those two hundred and sixty different sustainable development goals out there, right?
二百六十种可持续发展目之中任意一个的软件，对吧？
if we're going to have a carbon trading market
如果我们要建立一个碳交易市场的话
we're going to need a distributed ledger system to be able to do that on a global scale
我们就将需要一个分布式账本系统来在全球范围内实现这一点。
if we're going to eliminate child labor in mines or on fishing boats or in other industries
如果我们要消除矿上、渔船上或其他行业的童工现象
it's going to be through technologies like this.
它也将通过向像这样的科技实现。
FIN act is a project that supports Micro finance institutions in giving out loans
FIN act是一个支持小额金融机构为最贫穷的人
and and tracking savings for the poorest of the poor.
提供贷款和跟踪储蓄的项目。
So it's very rewarding to be able to make these services available to the poor.
所以，能够让穷人享受到这些服务，是非常有意义的。
Because if you don't have savings, if you don't have loans,
因为如果你没有储蓄，没有贷款，
if you don't have remittances, that's money transfers,
没有汇款，也就是转账，
then you don't have contact the global economy and you can't profit
那你就和全球经济脱节了
when your boat doesn't rise when everybody else's boat rises.
在大家都向前一步时，你原地踏步，因而你就无法获利
In the case of this project, you're connecting the empowerment
在这个项目中，你要把最贫困的人的赋能
of the poorest of the poor with the empowerment of the software developers.
和软件开发者的赋能联系起来。
And you're doing both of them in the context of a community.
而你是在一个社区的环境下完成这两件事的。
So there are really wonderful parallels between open source software and micro finance.
所以，开源软件和小微金融之间真的有奇妙的相似之处。
Being part of that, it just gives me a great feeling
作为其中一员，
that we've been able to change the world for the better
我们让世界变得更好，这种感觉很棒
A lot of our software helps developing countries.
我们的很多软件都在帮助发展中国家。
The great strides the world has made today in the last 20 years of globalization,
在过去20年的全球化进程中，当今世界取得了巨大的进步，
with the developing countries growing and advancing on providing better living conditions
发展中国家在不断发展、进步，人民生活水平逐步提高
and better economic advancement for its populations
经济发展欣欣向荣
That's a result of the Free software movements.
这是自由软件运动的成果之一。
And Apache had a big hand in that.
Apache 在其中发挥了巨大的作用
I feel very strongly.
我的感觉非常强烈。
The only thing that will save us as a species from our own internal greed
唯一能把我们这个物种从我们自身内在的贪婪
and hatred and the distance that we put between human hearts.
和仇恨，并消除人与人之间冷漠的唯一办法
And I occasionally I'm chided because I am very sensitive person and have thin skin.
有时大家责备我敏感、脸皮薄
And they say, you need thicker skin.
他们说，你脸皮应该再厚点。
Now thicker skin puts more distance between human hearts.
现在 ，厚脸皮让大家更生疏了
It allows more space for “not like me”.
让大家更讨厌“我”
It allows more space for “us versus them”.
在“我们“与“他们”之间筑就了一面墙
And that will be our undoing, not just as technologists but as a species.
而这将是我们的败笔，不仅仅是作为技术专家，更是作为一个物种。
And we are at a crucial point in our evolution, I believe,
而我相信，我们正处于进化的关键时刻，
where we need to start caring more about each other and less about profit.
此时我们需要开始更多地关心彼此，而不只是利益。
And the Apache way voices one part of that,
而Apache之道表达了其中的一部分意思。
I think in a very powerful way.
我认为以一种非常强大的方式。
When we put community above code,
当我们把社区放在代码之上的时候，
that gives us the opportunity to have a place
这就给了我们一个机会，
where people can be passionate about solving other people's problems.
让人们在这里可以满怀激情地去解决其他人的问题。
That is one element of good empathy.
而这是好的同理心的要素之一。